So we are talking about value functions okay
people remember value functions so we defined
value functions we said
V pi of S equal to expected value of pi right.
And then we defined Q pi
right good, so now we are going to start unrolling
their expectation and so people remember this
expression right so all of you are clear about
it so I don't have to explain what is happening
there again right so V pi of s is means starting
in state s following policy pi . Thereafter
and taking the expectations of the, the returns
that I am getting I am going to start unrolling
this right so what does it what does it look
like so
i am going to say V pi of s equal to, yes
What can I write here, I GT plus s1 right
but what is what would be the value of GT
plus for the expected value of GT+1. V pi
of whatever state you land up in right so
let us go I am going to say that this is equal
to
V pi of s prime were s prime is the state
I am going to add up and we will quantify
s prime in a minute right so, so people agree
with me on this right is s prime is the state
I go to from s right so I can take this summation
and write it like this. Everybody onboard
okay great so now I need a slight slight of
hand here right so I took GT and then I wrote
it as one term plus the expected value of
GT but that is fine because I am anyway going
to take a expectation eventually right so
this is slight reordering of the expectations
right instead of taking an expectation of
the full expression.
I took the expectation of the inner one alone
but one thing you have to remember is it is
only a partial expectation because s prime
can change right so for me to get the full
expectation I need to condition on s prime
also
That is why this expression is still inside
the expectation so if this has been the full
expectation I could have taking it out, out
of the expectation since it is still only
partially conditioned so I need to conditioned
on the full thing okay so now I have to write
it out so that will get rid of the expectations
okay so one way of writing out this expectation
is to think of it like a generative process
okay.
So remember what did I say we are going to
do we'll start in state s right then select
actions according to policy pi right and measure
the, expected return right so you are starting
in state is and the selecting actions according
to policy pi.
So what does that mean
using pi right and I am selecting actions
according to policy pi so let us say I pick
some action a right so now what I am going
to do I am going to get some reward corresponding
to that RT plus yeah the RT plus 1 will give
me something that corresponds to that reward
so but then before I can find out what RT
plud 1 this I need to specify what the next
state is going to be so I need this.
So taken action a then okay I determine what
s prime is and then I determine
What
but I already determined what s prime is it
so
I can do this
right so this is one step I am taking a pick
an action a according to pi right now that
is going to cause a transition to some s Prime
according to this P that we have there right
and once I know what the S prime is I can
figure out what the expected reward will be
as well as V pi s prime because I know what
s prime is is so what is the probability that
this will be my return is this times the probability
I will pick action a so this whole thing gives
me the probability that this will be my expected
return okay so now i have to do this overall
all possible outcomes.
So basically a sum over s prime okay is it
clear how we got this right this one right
so I have a s a right that I picked a a first
then I pick an s Prime according to p now
I have a SA S prime right so what I need to
do is figure out what this expectation of
RT plus 1 would be right so that is given
in my MDP right the expectation of RT plus
1 would be given SA S prime what is the reward
so that is this expectation I've written it
here expectation of r given SAS prime right
and then the future is gamma v pi s prime
so that S Prime has already been fixed so
I can just add the gamma v pi s prime here.
So the probability that this will be the outcome
right is the probability of s prime given
S and A time's the probability of picking
A given S .
So all these things put together gives me
the probability that this will be the outcome
right so that is the expected outcome for
one choice of A and one choice of S prime
so I'll have to sum this overall choices of
S prime and all choices of A for me to get
the overall expectation so that is essentially
what I've done here summed over x prime summed
over a .
This is nice right so we written V pi in terms
of V pi. So this, this system of it is a system
of equations right you can see there is a
system of equations that you have one equation
for every, every state how many variables
are there number of as many variables as there
are number of states the number of states
is not the variable that is also fixed as
many variables as number of states and what
is a very we here V pi of s is the variable.
So essentially so instead of thinking of it
as a function now I can think of it as a collection
of variables right one for each state right
and I have N such equations and N such variables
and can I solve it. Depends on what, its linear
N variables N equations so when can you not
solve it yeah then, then then yeah so when
we get dependent columns and so it becomes
redundant so you have multiple solutions and
sorts of three so it turns out as I'll show
you in the next class right the system of
equations have a unique solution always right
by virtue of the fact that the P that you
are using is stochastic so the rows of that
P matrix will sum to one right so by virtue
of that fact we can actually go back and show
that there will be a unique solution I will
just need to write, write is slightly different
in a different notation for us to see that
so I will do that in the next class right
so this is pretty much has a unique solution
and this is sometimes known as
The Bellman Equation for V pi after the Richard
Bellman who's one of the pioneers in the field
of stochastic dynamic programming okay. Like
ways you can write a bellman equation for
Q pi okay. Anyone wants to tell me about the
bellman equation for Q pi would be
No think of it in the generative process right
so what is the first thing you do when you're
thinking about Q pi SA .They start with yes
I pick a right I mean it is fixed so there
is no summing over there right it's S and
A is picked right so what do I have to sum
over next only the s primes because this pi
a s is out of the picture here right because
I have already picked A right . So I do not
need to I do not need to sample from pi they
already pick case so I just start my summing
over s prime.
Right now, now SA is prime are all fixed right
so I can write expected value of R given SA
s prime plus gamma times.
Now the interesting question is what goes
there I could write V pi and it will be perfectly
correct but I will not be writing Q pi in
terms of Q pi.
Summation over all actions
This is the Bellman Equation for Q pi okay.
So this should also give you one, one more
ancillary equation there which is.
And that is the way Q and V are related and
what about Q pi can you write Q pi in terms
of V pi. That's exactly what the earlier equation
was the Bellman Equation substitute the last
summation with V pi and that is essentially
Q pi in terms of V pi. Right so I cannot write
Q pi S a in terms of V pi s so it has to be
in terms of V pi of the subsequent state right
but V pi is I can write in terms of Q pi oops
sorry.